Hey, Mr. Hitoma.
What is it, Haneda?
Is it okay to have just one
graduation ceremony for Isaki?
Most people only ever get one.
We heard about it from Isaki.
Once she graduates,
she's going to become two people.
But until the two of them turn human,
they can't both exist at the same time.
I get it. That's what you mean.
This is Isaki's only chance,
so we should hold two graduations for her!
The next full moon's four days from now!
That'll be the last chance
for us to meet the other Isaki.
The school's real graduation ceremony
isn't for another week.
Why don't we hold our own ceremony
on the full moon in four days?
You're right. I think that's a great idea.
It almost reminds me of a wedding!
The kind with two ceremonies! How lovely!
Mr. Rei, what kind of
wedding would you prefer?
W-We're talking
about graduations right now!
Let's get back on topic and think
about what to do for Isaki's graduation!
While we're at it, why
don't we make it a surprise?
I like it! I'm all for a good surprise!
She won't know what's coming to her!
That's that, then!
Let's keep it a secret
from her until then!
Good morning.
Huh? Everyone's here early today.
Mathematics
I'm studying for my entrance exams.
Bowledoodle's so cute!
Mr. Rei! I love, love, love you!
The Misanthrope and the Comet's Pilgrimage
Episode 10
A surprise graduation ceremony, huh?
If it's in the classroom,
she might find out while we set up.
That's the biggest issue here.
We need to find somewhere
that Isaki wouldn't go.
How about the empty
classroom next to the library?
She might find out
when she goes to the library.
What about the conference room?
It's too close to the teachers' office.
We can't be too rowdy
with the other teachers nearby.
Where should it be, then?
How about the A/V room?
Good idea!
It's soundproof, and we
can use the projector!
Sounds good to me!
I think so, too.
Yeah, sounds like our best choice.
What do you think?
I like the idea, too.
I'll find out if we can use
the A/V room that day.
Thanks, Mr. Hitoma!
What kinda ceremony will it be for Ichaki?
I propose that we make it a fun one!
A serious ceremony will emphasize
what a big milestone it is.
They both have their charms, don't they?
I like the do-it-yourself feel this has.
I'll have to do all I can to make it
a good graduation ceremony.
Advanced Class
Um...
I feel like everyone's been
acting distant to me lately.
What?
Not to mention they all run
off somewhere after school.
I-I don't think that's true.
I don't have much time left
to spend with them.
But now they're all treating me
differently than before.
I can't help but feel
like they're avoiding me...
Ohgami, do you mind if I share
how you feel with the others?
What?
Well...
If they really are avoiding me,
I don't think I could ever recover.
I can guarantee that's not the case.
Still...
Don't worry!
That's definitely not what's going on!
R-Really?
Yeah! Yep! Uh-huh!
If you say so...
Then sure, go ahead.
Thanks, Ohgami!
You just wait right here!
A-Are you all right, Mr. Hitoma?!
Di... Di... Di...
Die?! Please don't die on me!
N-No... Directly to the A/V room...
Huh?
A/V Room
Can I go inside?
Yeah.
Here I go...
Excuse me...
Congratulations on graduating!
We're sorry we made you worry!
U-Um...
We're sorry.
You know how tomorrow's the full moon?
So we were planning on holding
a graduation ceremony for the other Isaki.
It was meant to be a surprise,
but not if it ends up worrying you. Isaki.
We want to congratulate both Isakis!
What?
Wow, it looks amazing!
You prepared all of this?
That's right!
We did our best to make it look cute!
It's fine, I guess.
Usami says that,
but she got pretty into it, too.
She was like, "I hope Isaki likes it!"
You don't need to tell her that!
Everyone... I'm so glad...
I was worried that you
were all avoiding me...
Everyone here is happy for you, Ohgami.
Yes! Thank you so much!
Well, all we're doing is having
the graduation ceremony tomorrow.
That may be so...
but I also thought it'd be nice
to let Isaki celebrate her graduation.
So I'm happy to see that
you all care so much about Isaki.
Don't get the wrong idea.
It's not just for Isaki tomorrow.
We care about the Isaki here, too.
That's right!
Don't forget about that!
To tell you the truth,
I was jealous of you and Isaki.
You both value and care
equally as much for each other.
I hope the two of you find
wonderful things in your futures!
Everyone... Thank you so much!
Happy Graduation Isaki
The Next Day
We will hereby award the diploma.
Diploma of Graduation
Isaki Ohgami
This certifies that the above individual has completed all of the prescribed studies.
Shiranui Private High School
Principal Shiro Karasuma
Graduating student, Isaki Ohgami.
Yes!
Isaki. Congratulations on graduating.
Thanks, Tobari.
I know that you'll do just fine
in the human world, Isaki.
You have my word.
I hope you lead a wonderful life
without any regrets.
Yeah!
Let's go grab some tasty desserts someday
when we're both human!
Yeah! One day for sure!
Thanks, everyone!
3 Days Later
We will hereby award the diploma.
Graduating student, Isaki Ohgami.
Y-Yes!
Isaki Ohgami.
Congratulations to you!
Principal!
Your graduation is the culmination
of your hard-earned efforts.
Nothing can change that fact.
I'll always remember
with pride having had you as a student.
I'm so sad that Ichaki's graduating!
Shut up, Machi!
I can't help it!
P-Please don't cry, Machi...
Now you're crying, Isaki!
Hey now, lay off her for today.
That's right. Aren't you sad, too, Sui?
Huh?!
Well...
It'll feel like something's missing.
Usami...
I'll be sad to miss out
on that surly affection of yours.
That's why?!
Mr. Hitoma!
Mr. Hitoma.
Thank you for everything
over the past two years.
Y-Yeah.
The Isaki within me has served
as a beacon of hope all this time.
You gave us the chance for Isaki
and I to come to an understanding.
I can't thank you enough.
Ohgami...
I should be thanking you.
Ohgami, your actions and outcomes came
from your own decisions.
I know that you two will do just fine.
I wish the two of you
happy lives going forward.
Mr. Hitoma.
Thank you very much!
My wish is the same!
Me, too!
Thank you all so much!
Congratulations once again!
Congrats!
Conference Room
Here we go!
Cheers, everyone!
Cheers!
Oh, human.
Not drinking much, are we?
C'mon, let me top you off.
Oh, thank you.
Wait, what are you
doing here, Miss Alice?!
Figured I'd celebrate
the occasion by sneaking in.
It looked like fun.
Is that really okay?
Yeah, it's fine.
I've cast a spell on myself so I can
only be seen by people I've met before.
Mr. Hitoma, who's this?
Huh?
He can see you just fine!
Hey, you're...
Miss Alice.
You shouldn't get
in a married man's face like that.
Huh? He's taken?
Mr. Hitoma, who is this?
Alice! How dare you show your face here!
Ugh, rats.
Oh, is she an acquaintance
of the principal?
Um... You could say that.
What's up?
It seems a friend
of the principal joined our party.
Never mind that, Satoru.
Yuki's already on her
sixth bottle, you know.
What?!
Gotta start with the most expensive
and delicious booze first...
Mr. Hoshino's got it rough...
I feel awful...
Get to work.
What?
Why are you slacking off?
I had too much to drink,
and now I'm hungover.
I'm getting second thoughts
about giving you this important job.
A job?
Hitoma. I want you to be my mailman.
Excuse me?
I wrote this letter while
I was doing my assignment.
I want you to deliver it
to Seiko in my place.
I would have liked to go myself,
but I didn't manage to graduate.
That's why I'm here to ask you, Hitoma.
Usami.
I want you to visit her grave.
School rules forbid any unauthorized
transmission of information off-campus.
I know that!
I figured it'd be a long shot.
I see.
Is it okay if I take this letter for now?
I'll see what the principal has to say.
Hitoma. Thanks.
I can't promise I'll deliver it to Seiko.
That's okay.
If you can't, then I'll accept it.
I have no other choice.
Okay. I'll try asking.
I take the bus from here?
The bus stop should be...
Oh, excuse me.
Could I ask you something?
I'm sorry.
I assumed you were a local.
No, we just happened to have the same
destination, and I know the way there.
My student asked me to deliver a letter
to the grave of her former caretaker.
Oh, what a wonderful teacher you are.
No, I wouldn't go that far.
I'm sure she would have
wanted to make the trip herself.
A letter for her caretaker's grave?
What an admirable girl.
Yes. Oh...
I forgot to introduce myself,
but my name is Rei Hitoma.
How polite of you.
As for me, I'm Sae Kizaki.
Ms. Kizaki?
What?
Um, would your mother's name
happen to be Seiko Kizaki?
What?
How do you know that?
Kizaki Family
Thank you for waiting. Go ahead.
Pardon my intrusion.
Mrs. Seiko, it's nice to meet you.
I'm Rei Hitoma, Usami's homeroom teacher.
Usami studies and works hard every day
with the help of her classmates.
As her teacher, I know she's diligent,
and cares very much for those around her.
I've come here today
with a letter from Usami.
I also received a letter
from her the other day.
It was a wonderful, honest,
and heartfelt letter.
I'm sure she's put great thought
into writing a wonderful letter for you.
I'm here in her place today,
but I know that she'll graduate
and visit in person one day.
Please wait until that day comes.
That's all from me.
Ms. Sae, thank you
for letting me pay a visit.
Not at all. I'm sure
my mother's delighted.
Cosmos...
Your student must have
known my mother very well.
What?
Cosmos were my mother's favorite flowers.
Their color reminded her of a stuffed
rabbit she had ever since she was a child.
But it had gone missing.
I looked for it before the funeral,
but I never found it.
I still regret not being
able to place it in her coffin.
Thank you for everything today.
Oh, thank you as well.
Please give my regards to your student.
Will do.
So long.
Excuse me!
The stuffed rabbit!
Actually, my student got it
as a gift from Mrs. Kizaki.
What?
It was fall two years ago.
My student visited her in the hospital,
and received it then.
So there's no need to worry!
Her stuffed rabbit is alive
and well to this very day!
Are you serious?
Yes! Usami's doing just fine!
What a relief.
Usami loves gossip,
so make sure she talks a lot to her.
Yes, I'll let her know.
Here's my contact information.
Please give this to your student.
She can reach out if she ever needs help.
Even if she doesn't,
I'd love to speak with her someday.
Yes, I'll make it happen.
Usami?
Did you deliver my letter to Seiko?
Yeah.
And as luck would have it,
I also ran into her daughter, Sae.
You got to meet Sae?!
Was she still a cheeky brat?
What exactly is your image of Ms. Sae?
A rotten brat who never listens.
What'd you two talk about?
She told me that Usami loves gossip,
so you should talk a lot to her.
Sae and Seiko are
the ones who love to gossip.
Also, I received Ms. Sae's
contact information.
Once you graduate, you can go meet her.
Yeah! Got it!
I'll try even harder!
I'll graduate, and see
how big Sae's gotten!
That's right.
Now I have another new goal!
Hitoma!
Thanks for going to talk with Sae!
I'd love to talk to Sae, too, someday!
Director's Office
Okay, let's begin our interview.
How was the past year for you?
I learned even more over the last year.
Weakness can be just as necessary a trait.
The people around you
will be there to help.
That shooting stars
in the summer are beautiful.
How important it is to think for yourself.
And that you should say what's
on your mind when you can.
I see. One last question.
Hey, Mr. Hitoma. Do you like humans?
I hate humans.
That said, I think there's more
about them I can forgive since last year.
I see. That's just like you.
Will there be any intermediate
students moving up this year?
There sure are.
And we're getting a new teacher.
Seriously?!
Seriously.
I wonder what they're like...
Want to see the file?
Can I really?!
You're all ears, huh?
You might want to take a moment
to prepare yourself, Mr. Hitoma.
This teacher will be the assistant
homeroom teacher for the advanced class.
So you mean I'll be
working with them a lot?
That's right.
Are you ready?
Yeah.
Take a look, then.
Resume
Furigana       Mirai Haruna
Full Name      Mirai Haruna
Mirai Haruna.
She'll be your junior co-worker
starting with the new term.
Next Episode:
The Misanthrope and the Nigh Past